[Music]
he h
hello welcome everybody Welcome to the
latest episode of ask abijit I hope
you're all doing
great so this is uh an episode in which
I will take questions from the live chat
only no other no other places only from
the YouTube live chat so before I start
doing that let's see who all is there on
the live chat I can see Manan Chopra I
am God Park Jim niharika Gupta samith
statement lus sahana Nat Aman rajput
Samar
acharia uh saja kapali Park Jim cave s
Aditi Somalia
miti uh as Prine Gap garti pramesh
samudra Das haray random skull anurag
brown boy in Malaysia Lawrence Kyer from
San Francisco California prush push cter
shria n Om beerer hello Deepak ragir
solanki Prashant Sharma geopolitical dub
hello Vladimir
Chava Ashish tiari Gio
Barat Arian kot K sumitra Munda rakit
Mishra red Hello yatia Aurora KL an
shubhankar Dr suak dager endan OAS super
Rex revolutionary Indian rakasi Raj
Panda utar s uh by
DHA and lots and lots of other people
Sonia
Sinha Shri ramachandra namaha lafy
07 Ashish
deika uh Lisa Rose Dr J Shankar Anushka
shaat kavia but and lots and lots of
other people Miguel Diaz hello everybody
else so I'm going to stop greeting you
all now otherwise I'll not do anything
else and let's get going with the
questions let us see what questions we
have
today um let's see let's see there is
havit Chava from London
hello okay all right let's let's take
some questions what are the
questions uh Vladimir chavas says what's
the nuisance that's going on in
Parliament Mr Modi Prime Minister Modi
is looking a little weaker
well I haven't been following What's
happen happening in Parliament I hear
the parliament session is on the way and
I do hear about I do hear you know
little birds chirping around about
what's going on on a day-to-day basis I
don't see what's happening on a
day-to-day basis you know what happened
today this time that time whatever but I
hear what's going on and it looks like
the opposition is emboldened because of
their much better performance this time
in the elections and Mr Modi seems to be
kind
of uh kind of not so much on the on the
front foot the way he he used to be so
it it does look like it does look like
uh he is kind of diminished a little bit
at least at least when it comes to
speaking on the floor of the house and
all that stuff uh and the opposition is
showing its muscle so to say making lot
of you know noise and Ruckus and
disrupting activities and interrupting
speeches and
cat calling and whatnot that's what I
hear I'm I've not seen any of that
that's what I've heard so U no surprise
there no surprise the opposition is is
has larger numbers now so they're going
to make their presence felt that's how
it
goes and when when they've done better
than the last time and they feel that
the that the ruling party is weaker and
it's a coalition government they're
going to press try and press home some
kind of Advantage so that's what's
happening right now no Big Sur prise
um overall I don't think this is a weak
government as such or it may look a
little diminished Mr Modi may look a
little weaker but overall I think it it
may be stable reasonably stable uh for
the foreseeable future so what really
matters is not what is said on the floor
of the Parliament House and what kind of
debates happen what really matters is
the policies that are implemented over
the next 5 years or as long as the
government stays in power you know it's
a government you never know so that's
what really matters so I am not
interested in what people are seeing in
Parliament and who's fighting and who's
shouting and who's not and all the who's
doing a walk out and what slogans are
being raised I don't care that doesn't
really matter what really matters is the
policies that are implemented going
forward and we have to see how how that
goes so that's my perspective thus far
it's it's very early days for the
current
government uh okay what other questions
do we have uh Prine garti new member
garti thank you so much welcome sir
um
okay VAB shind says what's your thoughts
on Tantra sadhana and various other
practices in sanatan Dharma which deals
with the dark side of the universe see
sir uh I have absolutely no
understanding of this I am uh even not
even a beginner in this I have no
knowledge of these things so I'm not
right the right to ask these questions I
apologize but I don't have an answer to
this I have no idea never tried it don't
know never studied
it
um mcloven says why is there a sudden
increase in racism against
Indians uh
look the nothing has really changed okay
uh the the perceptions that existed 20
years ago still exist uh the the part of
the world that that's been ruling the
planet for the past 500 years it
obviously believes that it is superior
right so the Europeans have been ruling
the world for the past 500 or so years
past five centuries or so and they
believe that they are superior because
they've been ruling the world for five
five centuries and it is it is their
belief that whatever physical Etc
attributes they have are superior so
white skin Etc is superior and darker
skin is inferior that sort of thing
that's standard classical uh racism and
I I believe there's some kind of racism
everywhere uh so that's always been
there and these days of late India's
economy has been growing India has been
taking very strong positions
geopolitically India has followed to cow
bend the knee when it comes to America's
demands Visa Russia Ukraine all that uh
and India is beginning to matter in in
certain ways and that obious viously is
going to ruffle feathers and the people
who have been ruling the world for five
centuries they will they will obviously
be uh you know they will not be happy
about this I mean how dare you rise up
we we destroyed you how how dare you
still exist stay in your land stay in
your lane don't get off the
reservation so it's because India is
growing and India is standing up for
itself to a certain extent that's why
these people feel the need to to put
India in its place and to put Indians in
in their place and nowadays there are so
many Indians on social media we are 1.4
billion of us and plus a diaspora
outside outside of the
subcontinent and U Indians are very
waser us very
opinionated and uh so so what what we
find is that Indians can often drown out
the opposing narrative just by sheer
volume of numbers I mean I mean we have
we've had some instances recently of
certain so-called comedians going all
hinduphobic and indob and uh the Indians
are very resourceful and those people's
uh dark past was was excavated and put
out in public and that sort of things so
so you see they don't they don't they
don't
expect Indians to be able to do this but
Indians are doing that so that that's
why you will see this re action you know
Action Reaction Newton's third law of
motion that sort of thing so it's it's a
good sign actually it tells you that
India is doing well and they don't like
the fact that India is doing doing well
and India is doing better than they
expected and India's projected to do
even better and India may end up by the
end of the century perhaps being the
largest economy in the world and that's
what really upsets them you know whoever
is indulging in racism so that's the
thing and it's no big de
I mean I'm not concerned it's always
been around and uh I mean if you travel
the world you will see
subtle uh elements of
racism sometimes subtly depending on
what circles you move in it may be
subtle it may be covered it may be
overed but it's always
around uh so yeah there you have there
you have
it Summit statement says what would you
expect from a leader who genuinely wants
to do something for for Arya ARA India
bhat the Indian civilization not the
nation state of India but the
civilization state of India that's what
suit statement is talking about listen
there are lots of people who who want
good things for Arya birth there are
lots of leaders who have good
intentions but intentions don't matter
what you fervently desire and wish for
doesn't matter what matters is the
quality of the leadership right
so what would you expect from a leader
who wants to do something for ARA worthy
you would expect that they will uh you
know Safeguard and and uh promote the
national interest as well as the
civilizational interest the national
interest is it pertains to the nation
state of India territorial
Integrity uh long-term National Security
uh
long-term prosperity for today's Indians
and their future generations and so on
and so forth there's a set of elements
that come with that taken together
constitute the national interest but
there is something more than that as
well which is the civilizational
interest in National interest you also
have
self-determination uh uh demographic
continuity cultural continuity all of
that and some of these elements are also
elements of the civilizational interest
so obviously would want a civilizational
Resurgence in India the oldest
civilization all of that so you would so
these are the things that a leader would
want to achieve if that leader genuinely
wants to do something for ARA the
problem is that there are lots of
leaders who genuinely wish well but they
don't even know what their civilization
is and some of them I'm not saying this
person or that person but some of them
perhaps many of them want to reform
Indian Society because in Indian societ
apparently is backward H and there are
lots of evils in Indian
Society so and apparently the believe
that these Evils are inherent to Indian
culture and so on so such leaders are
problematic okay those who want to
reform Indian society and Indian culture
and make it better and all that the
problem is not within India's culture
the problem is the problems have Arisen
because of colonialism India has to be
decolonized India doesn't have to be
uplifted and made less backward
civilization yes economically yes we are
very backward the GDP per capita is very
low so a leader who genuinely wants to
do something needs to have a
multifaceted approach it can't be a
monochromatic approach I will only work
on the economy and I will only do
something about the
military the the culture can go to hell
I mean there are such leaders around
okay one can I'm sure there are such
leaders around let's let's put it that
way so that's a problem see you you need
leaders who have a 360 degree approach
everything needs to be taken care of and
that's what in the government you have
Ministries don't you so if you have one
leader obviously one leader can't take
care of everything but he or she can
delegate work to each Ministry and their
job is to do that job right that sort of
thing um so I'm sure there are lots of
leaders who who are who mean well and
who have great intentions but at the end
of the day you have to be able to
perform and get things done that is what
truly defines the quality of your
leadership so if you think back about
the great leaders of History forget
about India bhat wassh think about
worldwide leaders okay think about
someone like Julius
Caesar okay he is considered to be one
of the great greats Alexander the Greek
is also allegedly one of the
greats uh who else who else do we have
Chandra gupt Mor his his Grand grandson
Ashok Moria keska the
great um and so many more chingis
Khan and chhatrapati shivaji Maharaj and
Napoleon and so on so forth imagine
living at a time when you have a leader
like that these leaders could genuinely
take the
world in in in their hands and and force
the world to to bend itself to their
will
that's what you genuinely need in a
leader intentions everybody has
intentions but it's it's very very
difficult to make a genuine change in
the world because the entire world is
geared towards inertia nobody wants to
change everybody wants to be comfortable
change is painful even good change even
change for the better is painful because
there are so many people in systems and
institutions ET that benefit from the
status quo think about it every single
politician who is in Parliament in India
today has come to power because of the
system the the the terrible system that
we have today do you think they will
want the system to change the system
that brought them to power so you see
that's the difficult job that a leader
has if a leader wants to make a genuine
change they have to go against the tide
and everybody will try to oppose them
that's what you want in a leader apart
from having the great best intentions so
today we don't have such leaders I can't
think of a single leader of that caliber
that the names that I just uttered I
can't think of of a single leader of
that caliber in the world today
anywhere okay so that's the
issue um hopefully some somebody emerges
from somewhere maybe somebody has
already somebody's already already
around that we're not aware of th thus
far but yes the task at hand is
immense okay bam vishwamitra says why do
you think of a defense manufacturing is
so weak China set a target of rolling
out hundreds of jets per year H hardly
produces 20 Jets a
year um it's because of see there are
multiple issues involved in this matter
first of all the Legacy issues we never
developed uh the
capacity whether it is H or wherever to
mass produce high quality stuff first of
all the the quality of our R&D research
and development I'm sure we have great
Engineers great scientists but if if
your requirements keep changing every
year and a half then you simply can't
develop anything and that's what
happened with the Tes fighter plane I
mean the program began in what 19 in the
19 late 7s 1970s or early 80s or
something like that and the first
flights took place in the first decade
of the 21st century right and obviously
a jet jet jet fighter plane developed is
a long process but it should not take
that long so what happened is that the
requirements were were repeatedly
changed over and over again the moment
there is a little bit of progress
they'll change some requirements okay
this should not be this long but that
long whatever whatever components so you
keep on changing that so you to keep on
redesigning from scratch so that's one
thing then it's well you know how it was
right the politicians used to benefit
from allegedly benefit from Kickbacks
coming in from abroad you buy foreign
foreign defense equipment you're going
to get some some cut and that that's why
you want to kill off your your domestic
capability if there is any so there was
that allegedly in the past okay and uh
once again look I am if you look at an
organization like
drdo uh it has let's say roughly 30,000
employees out of which 25,000 are not
Engineers or
scientists okay
drdo has an has a strength of roughly
30,000 of which 25,000 are not
scientific or engineering staff so I
don't know what they are doing and why
they exist in that organization and what
they are being paid for so significant
amount of the budget which is allegedly
science budget or or or or R&D budget
actually goes into these salaries of
these these non-scientific
non-engineering people so there are all
these issues and then an organization
like DL has lots of layers of
bureaucracy uh and the bureaucrats
generally are non-engineering
non-scientific individuals just like the
ASI where the bureaucrats who run the
ASI they don't know anything about
archaeology they're just IAS officers
that sort of thing so you have all these
terrible Legacy issues there is a
desperate need for reform everywhere and
the pace of Reform is is a snail space
and that's why we have these issue
now right now we have a reasonably good
fighter plane that we producing the
tages but we are putting out what 16 or
20 per year I mean now that we know how
to build this thing and we have an
assembly line why can't we duplicate or
triplicate the assembly line and and
increase the production to much to much
higher uh levels so that we can even
take care of export orders whenever they
come in if we have any and so on so
forth I don't know what the deal is
obviously you know quantity has a
quality of its own uh the Tes fighter
plan what's the cost I'm not sure what
the cost is maybe 50 million a piece or
something I'm guessing at least 20
million a piece
dollars uh so why not have a couple
hundred of those I
know that you know they are not fifth
generation fighter planes but quantity
always has a quality of its own so I
would like to see much greater turnover
every year number of production just
produced but like I said we have all
these issues have just Pro probably just
scratched the surface of the problem but
these are the reasons why our defense
manufacturing is is weak it's
backward uh and it's not just about
fighter planes we could be developing so
many things I mean why don't we have our
own howitzers artillery various kinds of
artillery why don't we produce our own
you know destroyers ships submarines why
don't we have dozens of these things why
don't we have uh we have good missile
systems and all but how many are we
producing I'm not sure so there's so
much we could do we should be completely
self-sufficient when it when it comes to
uh ammunition when it comes to arms when
it comes to drones we should have
families of drones not just one kind of
drone but dozens of kinds of drones
medium altitude high high
endurance high altitude high endurance
drones and whatnot we should be
developing all of this and we have the
the talent there is that and obviously
when it comes to attracting Talent when
you pay very small salaries do you think
you're going to you're going to be able
to attract the best of the best no the
best of the best will go abroad and work
for other countries so these are some of
the problems which are cause which are
at the root of this issue and I'm
telling you I'm just barely scratching
the surface of the
problem revolutionary Indian says why
didn't you read The Communist Manifesto
of course I've read it I've got it
somewhere thin little
book how do I describe that book look I
can explain communism in in one sentence
perhaps what communism is or
Marxism it is a sociopolitical toolkit
whose only objective is to bring to
power a very small number of people and
keep them in power at the expense of
everybody else that is what Marxism is
uh I'm not sure why you why you are
assuming I haven't read The Communist
Manifesto I assure you my dear sir I
have read The Communist
Manifesto A long time ago and I still
have it for reference so look I have
it's it's not like I am anti-communist
or anti-marxist or antisocial or pro-
capitalist or whatever I mean look at
the condition of capitalism a capitalist
country like the us today if you are
let's say an Indian immigrant in this
capitalist Paradise the United States
okay and let's say you are a highly
skilled person and you're earning
$100,000 per year after taxes how much
do you have left maybe 70,000 or
so 70 65,000 or something after taxes
perhaps you will have left I'm I'm being
optimistic here and then if you cut out
if you if you take out utilities and
whatnot and your insurance and uh health
and dental and groceries and rent and
everything you may be left with maybe
five or $10,000 if you are if you are
really disciplined okay so you are
essentially living a handt mouth
existence if you are a single individual
single male or female living on his or
her own the moment you have a spouse and
that spouse is dependent on you you are
in deep Waters and God forbid you have a
child good God what are you going to do
both of you going to have to go going to
have to work and then you have to
Outsource the uh upkeep the the the
raising of your child to complete
strangers and then you know what happens
kids develop green hair and blue hair
and they chop off bits and pieces of
their Anatomy that's what happens uh so
the US is no capitalist Paradise today
and people who aren't highly skilled
have to work like two three jobs a day
and sleep four hours a day just to put
two or three meals on the table for
their kids it's it's a disaster today so
whether it's communism whether it's
capitalism no matter what system it is
it can be subverted it can be corrupted
communism has this track record of pro
of producing disasters over and over
again should I give you the examples
look at what happened to the USSR a
collectivized society okay the
dictatorship of the proletariat it was
the the you know the objective of
Communism is to bring a very small
number of people to power and maintain
them in power that is the poit Bureau
okay that that small group of
individuals and their minions are the
bureaucracy okay and the USSR was a
collectivized society so nobody had any
savings nobody had any private property
everything belonged to the state so all
the savings of the people of the USSR
for seven decades were the property of
the Chinese of of the the of the
Communist Party of the USSR and after
the collapse of Communism what happened
all of that property was given away to
to so-called
oligarchs all of that all of the savings
of the people of the USSR seven plus
Decades of savings were
just handed off to a small number of
people that's what happened when there
was a transition from communism to uh
ISM apparently and communism itself
failed in the USSR
communism as failed everywhere else
whether it is Cambodia I mean look at
what happened in Cambodia look at what
happened Angola look at the condition of
Cuba obviously I will not blame
communism for what happened to Cuba it
is the US sanctions that have destroyed
Cuba and so on but overall it doesn't
ever produce great results and then they
said no it was not the right kind of
Communism we'll next the next time we do
it we'll do it the right way and
capitalism also can be subverted the
same way look at what's happening in the
US I mean it's a disaster right now so
it doesn't matter what system it is any
system can be sub
corrupted yeah whether it is communism
whether it is capitalism whether it is
dictatorship whether it is democracy if
you do it right it may all work all of
these systems may work if you do it
wrong any of these systems could give
you a terrible result so that's what I
shall say about this in
brief Stephen Dominic says can we ever
go to another galaxy or Universe okay
let's not talk about other universes we
have never seen Another Universe we can
only see a small portion of the universe
we
inhabit what how far can we see we can
see uh as far as about 40 47 billion
light years away okay in in any
direction so the diameter of the
observable universe is about 94 or so
billion light years so that's all we can
see it's only a small portion of the
actual Universe we inhabit and we don't
know what's beyond okay if there is
anything beyond or not we can conjecture
we can speculate but we don't know so
other universes let's not discuss it
because that is there is no
observational evidence which means it is
not science we're discussing we only
discussing fantasy if you're talking
about other universes what about other
galaxies look
theoretically there is nothing that
prevents us from going to another galaxy
um let's say you you develop a you know
a spacecraft that travels at let's say
30% the speed of light it's possible
it's possible with with let's say
technology that's almost here
uh you can use light sale technology to
accelerate a spacecraft a small
spacecraft to very quickly to speed off
about 30% the speed of light using uh
gigawatt lasers that you shine on the
light sale can be done we are almost
there we may have the technology in
about 10 years and then you will be the
spacecraft will be traveling at 30% or
maybe even 40% the speed of light and it
can reach the nearest star system in
about 20 or 30 years Proxima centor
which is your
neighbor your back backd door neighbor
that's it the next star the nearest star
uh
the okay which is about four point
something light years away four point
something light years from here from
where we are the Galaxy the our home
galaxy The Milky Way is what 100,000
light years I think in diameter if I'm
not mistaken if if my memory serves me
right and the nearest galaxy Andromeda
is of the order of a few million light
years from here so it would take at 30%
the speed of light about 3 to four
million years to reach that that's it
that's
all uh so how old is the human species
Homo sapiens about 400,000 years 0.4
million years
okay and if you talk about the if you go
back four million years in the past we
we were at a stage in our Evolution
where our ancestors were the same as the
ancestors of the
chimpanzees so by the time your
spacecraft reaches Andromeda 4 million
years in the future we may have evolved
that much that our descendants will
think of the their ancestors who sent
the
spacecraft as the the the the way we
think of
chimpanzees so it's possible technically
theoretically with current present day
technology but it is
Impractical so you can send a small
spacecraft you can even magnify your
your lasers and have a large number of
lasers and concentrate that on a largest
solar sale and send human beings into
into space at that speed but will they
survive for billion four million years
or so uh will they be able to replicate
I mean reproduce and survive and all
that in that small thing capsule Etc
lots of questions it's Poss so the
answer in short is it is possible but it
is extremely impractical with present
day technology but let's say we have
superum species in the future super
human super intelligent humans or let's
say you have artificial super
intelligence which may be around the
corner then you could be able to do
things that we can't imagine today like
punch a hole through space time create
an Einstein Rosen Bridge a
wormhole and then do weird stuff with a
wormhole which leads to extremely
paradoxical situations such as
relativistic well essentially time
travel could be possible so you could do
stuff that you can't imagine today if
you have ASI artificial super
intelligence and that may open up a
whole range of possibility that we can't
even possibly imagine today so that's
what I'll say with present day
technology and understanding we can do
it but we can do it extremely slowly and
it's not
practical okay
um inia says why is the government not
taking any action against influencers
that are spreading fake fake news and
are brainwashing people and these
individuals apparently seem to be funded
by the West well you see in India is a
wonderfully Democratic nation in India
we have something called freedom of
speech and freedom of expression which
means that you have the right to say
whatever you
want
okay um imagine you go to China and
imagine in China somebody says something
about President shenping what's going to
happen let's say someone goes on on
their Twitter what's it calledo or
whatever it's called and they say that
ping is a dictator down with Chen ping
what's going to happen 15 minutes later
the cops are going to turn up at the his
or her home and that guy or girl or
whoever it is is going to be behind bars
for a significant percentage of his or
her lifetime that's what will happen
guaranteed to happen in China that's a
nation without without free speech
that's not a democracy but in our
wonderful more evolved Nation bhat wor
India secular socialist Nation uh we
have freedom of speech which means you
can say whatever you want you can say
anything you wish about the Prime
Minister and nothing's going to happen
to
you okay uh and that is the exact
opposite of a
dictatorship but it has gone to such
such a level that you can even say
outright right outright lies about the
Prime Minister about the government
about National about the National
Security situation about the State of
Affairs in India you can say outl
lies and when certain individuals who
have very large amount of you know who
have a very large following uh and these
are individuals apparently may have some
kind of agenda they may have some kind
of funding from which comes in from
outside or whatever then they'll be able
to do this at scale large scale and if
the government cracks down on these
individuals and the entire Western media
is going to start howling in chorus
saying that India is becoming a fascist
Nation India's democracy is backsliding
here is
evidence that so and so person
innocently said something very very
truthful and genuine and see the
government cannot handle any criticism
it will not allow any criticism so
because we are we don't want to face
that criticism from the Western media
and governments we are no doing nothing
about this and it's not I'm not trying
to say that the government of India is
being weak need and is giving
in okay uh there are real problems the
West is waiting
for even a even the smallest opportunity
to take some kind of action against
India the West considers India to be a
problem the West considers India to be a
long-term threat and adversary and uh
competitor if India just keeps on
growing the way it's going growing even
if it keeps on growing at 6% per year in
20 30 years India is going to be ahead
of China India is going to be a
significant problem for them so they
would like to nip that in the bud right
now and how do you do that you do that
by by undermining India's economy by
undermining India's economic growth and
you can do that through what you know
soft sanctions hard sanctions whatever
but for that you need an excuse you need
a
pretext so let's say the Indian
government does take some actual action
against the terrorists in Manipur
imagine the kind of sanctions they'll
dump on India imagine India puts a
couple of fake news spreading
influencers takes some legal action
against fake news spreading
influencers then there could be action
against India of some kind and so on the
west is just waiting for the slightest
opportunity to pounce on India and I
believe me they have the ability to
completely destroy the economy of almost
any
Nation they can take a prosperous Nation
and reduce it to Venezuela or Cuba like
situation they did that to Cuba they did
that to Venezuela
Venezuela's you know hyperinflation and
all that is not because of socialism
it's because of us
sanctions okay if Iran's economy is is
is not doing well at all it's not
because Iran it's not because of the
whatever regime you have in Iran it's
because of American
sanctions they can destroy a nation
entirely
which sitting here living our
comfortable lives we don't realize they
can reduce a nation to Hell in a matter
of a couple of months so the Indian
government has to be extremely careful
we have to swallow this sort of pain
until we grow to a 105 trillion dollar
economy uh level and develop some
genuine hard power along the way that
military might military muscle which
comes in a variety of shapes and forms
so that's what needs to happen and right
now we are simply not strong enough to
stand up to the West we have to
understand this we are not a superpower
my dear friends we are not even close to
dream of dream about being a
superpower we are nowhere we are just a
regional
power okay and we may be potential great
power in the future maybe in 10 years
time right now we are merely a regional
power we they are nowhere close to visha
Guru or superpow whatever I don't know
why Indians want to they keep on
throwing these wild Fantastical things
about India as a superpower or Rising
superpower no you're not you're nowhere
close to being a superpower so we have
to be
realistic that we are nowhere close to
being able to stand up to the US and
that's why we have to act Meek it is in
our interest to keep our head down and
just do the work of growing the economy
for the next 20 30 years it's going to
take time there's no shortcuts my
friends so that in short is the
deal all right
um Sunny says what can we do about
China
China exists first of all recognize the
China exists and secondly recognize that
it is about four times more powerful
than India these are facts if you take
the hard power score of India it is
about
4.9 if you look at the hard power score
of China it's about 17 or something it's
almost four times that of India that is
how much more powerful China is compared
to India we have to recognize this fact
okay and understand that whenever Wars
are if you look at the past three 5,000
years of
History Wars are won by technology Wars
are not won through some 's bravery
everybody is brave if a man has the has
the bra has has the courage to go and go
into battle knowing that he will die or
he could die that is bravery enough
everybody is
brave what really matters is your
technological prowers technological
advancements technological ability that
is historically that has been the
determinant of Victory or or defeat in
war or in battles
so what we have to do about China is we
have to develop our military and other
technological press that's what we have
to
do saying that our soldiers are brave
and blah blah blah of course they are
brave but that is not going to guarantee
any Victory we have to develop the
technological prw and we have to surpass
the Chinese and we are not there we are
not anywhere close to surpassing the
Chinese so what can we do we can thank
the gods that we have a Himalayan border
region between India and Chinese
occupied Tibet where technology has to
kind of take a back foot and human the
quality of the human capital comes to
the four if it comes to Battlefield
tactics and Battlefield
outcomes but um and yet China is way
ahead of India so what we have to do is
first of all we have to close the gap
between in in hard power by growing the
economy and and and growing the military
and and increasing the military budget
okay and secondly we have to develop the
technologies that will allow us to
properly compete against China that's
what we have to do and we have to do
this
rapidly not over okay next 20 years
we'll do something no no no this is
urgent this is critical trust me this is
critical you never know with China when
they could start a new
misadventure so that's what we have to
do about China stop living in la la land
in visha Guru land super power land be
realistic understand you're the smaller
guy right now and try and become
bigger do that do the hard work and do
it on an urgent basis on priority that's
what we have to
do
okay
um what else what
else let's talk about Cricket cile says
is jpit bura the greatest bowler ever
the accuracy and ball control he has is
impeccable the skills which he has are
close to none look I think it's too
early to say that he is the greatest
bowler ever
or what I would say that look I I have
been watching Cricket since for a very
long time I remember as a kid watching
the 1992 World Cup okay the only good
thing that happened for us was we
defeated
Pakistan um so I've seen them all I've
seen Imran Khan bowling like I've seen
Wasim wakar bowling I have seen ctly
Ambrose I've seen Malcolm Marshall I
have seen Walsh I've
seen MRA I've seen them all I've seen
Kapil Dev prabakar
shrat so I would say it's it's early
days to to start claiming that J J bumra
is the best ever let him play his entire
career let him let his career come to an
end then we can make an
assessment I would say he's probably the
best India has ever produced that I can
already see that but is it the best ever
of all time I would say he may be better
than Wasim and wakar because those two
gentlemen were the champions of of ball
tampering and they learned it from the
great man himself Imran Khan
naazi so I would be uh they were great
of course Wasim and wakar I think Wasim
was even better than wakar and the but
ball tampering that that shadow always
will lie over their heads okay the
pakistanis ball tampering match fixing
that Spectre will always haunt them for
good
reason I would say so that's why I would
say that bumra I would rank him higher
than Wasim and wakar but let's see how
he goes how he performs through the rest
of his career but is he better than
someone like Ambrose I think Ambrose
perhaps is the best ever in my opinion
out of those who I've seen okay and
brose perhaps uh but over time let's see
will jpit bura get 400 plus test wickets
and and similar achievements in udis and
all that we don't know I hope he does
it'll be great for us it'll be great for
him I like the guy very much great guy
so let's see I think it's too early to
pass judgment but he definitely I would
say is a better is probably the best
bowler India has produced better than
shrat better than prakar better than
Zahir Khan better
than capil Dev oh yes I would say he
better than
kabil but worldwide globally we still
have to
see okay
um
um okay what else lots of questions of
course ad says can the US fall as an
Empire what will be the consequences of
it
falling look any Empire can fall any
Empire can collapse and it's it's
something if you study history you will
see that every Empire eventually does
decline and fall and obviously when it's
declining it will try its best to
prevent the decline and to avert the
fall which means it's going to lash out
in all directions so every Empire
eventually does fall you said see that
over and over again in India itself this
Indian subcontinent we had huge Empires
that came that eventually fell generally
on average an empire in in India lasts
about two or three centuries two two and
a half or three centuries as an Empire
then after declining it may become a
kingdom again for another Century or so
but it's no longer an Empire so an
Empire typically lasts two or three
centuries and you see the same kind of
thing in China as well two or three
centuries um of course the cholas as a
dynasty ruled for almost 2,000 years in
some form or
but as an Empire they ruled for about
two or three centuries in the form of an
Empire uh and so on so forth the Roman
Empire how long did that last two three
centuries maybe the Eastern Roman Empire
lingered for a much longer time which is
the Byzantine Empire and you have
similar things in other parts of the
world so
Empires will eventually fall now how
long has the US Empire existed the US
Empire essentially came into being in
let's say the date of the year of birth
is 1944 when you had the official
coronation when they took the crown from
the British and put it on their heads
the the West failure thing right the
yeah the Treaty of West failure when the
US dollar was agreed upon was accepted
as the Global Currency and blah blah
blah in 58 was the final humiliation of
the British and the French as well and
they seized to be
uh first class uh Global geopolitical
power uh so the US has
been the global Empire let's say or the
successor of the uh British Empire since
44 which is about 80 years ago is it 80
roughly this is 2024 that's about 80
years ago but as an Empire not Global
Empire but as a regional Empire they
have been around for much longer I mean
um they went to war with everybody in
North America and defeated everyone so
let's say another 100 years have elapsed
since the Americans have been an Empire
if you look at North America I mean
where's the map here's the map let's go
to the map North America so the US uh do
do we have uh some kind of image of the
progression territorial expansion of the
US it used to be much smaller they they
fought other countries they fought the
Mexicans they fought the French they
fought fought everybody they stole the
plundered Land from the natives and they
expanded rapidly so that was an
expansion that took at least 100 years
so you can say that the US Empire has
been in place in power for about roughly
180 or 200 years so we are kind of there
perhaps when an Empire starts declining
uh
generally so the US can certainly fall
as an
Empire and in the modern day con context
what the word superpower essentially
means
Empire uh so how could they fall is the
question well one one thing is that
their currency May no longer be
recognized as a global Reserve currency
other other nations may start trading in
other currencies and no longer
prioritize the US dollar that could be
one factor that could uh cause the fall
or or the decline rapid decline of the
US Empire uh the US has Global power
projection capabilities it has more than
800 extra territorial military bases
around the world so if that is impacted
that could obviously significantly Dent
their Global power projection ability
and their their Global superpower status
so all these things could contribute to
the fall of the us as an Empire all the
uh Supply chains that has build up all
the uh
networks uh trade networks agreements
treaties all of that all of that
together forms the superstructure the
infrastructure of EMP EMP and if that is
affected in some way or the other the
Empire May decline so right now um if
you look at the US its influence its
Prestige is diminishing but its power
hasn't diminished the US dollar is still
the global Reserve currency very much so
and the power projection abilities
capabilities of the US are unmatched and
they are not declining so overall U it's
not anywhere close to falling but it can
fall what are the consequences
chaos if when whenever Empires fall
there's chaos there a
significant period of time of turmoil I
mean if you look at the Chinese Imperial
Cycles whenever an an Empire or whenever
a dynasty dynastic Cycles right whenever
a dynasty loses the Mandate of Heaven
let's say like the Chinese say then the
dynasty Falls the Empire Falls and then
there's a period of chaos 50 years 100
years maybe 150 years until a new
Dynasty arises new Empire arises and
there a new Imperial cycle dynastic
cycle so that is typically what happens
everywhere so if the US Falls as an
Empire there's going to be a period of
chaos a sustained period of chaos maybe
half a century maybe a century or so
until a new power emerges
so it won't be good for the world okay
there may
be uh there may be uh hegemonic Power
they may ride rough FR over everybody
they may you know proper dictatorships
around the world they may interfere in
everybody's Internal Affairs uh they
bully Nations and much more they may
destroy Nations flatten Nations like
they did to Iraq Libya Etc but if they
Decline and fall it's going to be even
more chaos worldwide that is the way it
is unless there's a there's right away
someone to replace it which is kind of
perhaps
unlikely okay
um prit Agarwal says how do we raise our
standards the Mind keeps dragging back
to the low ordinary behaviors there has
to be I I think it's a great question
maybe I should do a separate video about
this after giving some thought to it but
let me give you some straight away a few
pointers uh you have to to change the
way you
think uh we generally tend everybody
everybody tends to think
emotionally uh everybody tends to the
thought process tends to be a knee-jerk
reaction to what's happening we don't
use uh scientific reasoning logical
reasoning we don't use Mental models to
approach problems and situations what is
the scientific process the the
scientific method we don't know what
that is it's not about uh creating a
body of knowledge of whatever the
scientific method is about asking
extremely uncomfortable questions when
it comes to any situation or problem
so that you get the correct information
out of it and then you can identify the
problem and maybe find ways to solve it
so uh there is that and obviously
raising your standards means discipline
discipline is extremely difficult
discipline comes through very small
things discipline comes through
extremely small decisions you would take
over and over again the choices that you
make on a daily basis the choices you
choose to make the systems you create
the processes you create in your life
the routines you uh follow all of
that and all of that also what you what
you consume the food you consume are you
consuming the right kind of food are you
consuming the right quantity of the
right kind of food and not just the food
you consume the reading material that
you can what do you read every day do
you scroll three hours a day on on
whatever screen you have on your on your
mobile device that is also consumption
what kind of entertainment choices do
you have do you watch some
some some whatever series on TV that
doesn't provide any value to you you
spend three four hours a day watching
whatever OT platform and some random
series all day is consuming information
or or entertainment mindlessly or are
you actually creating something are you
actually trying to solve some problem
and create something of value for
yourself your family Society country
whatever all of these things you to ask
yourself
right you to ask yourself what if you
ask yourself what three things should I
do that will make me proud one years one
one year down the
line what three things should I stop
doing which will make the biggest
difference in my life in in one year's
time and so on so forth these are the
things you to do so maybe I should make
a separate video about this but I think
uh I I hope what I just said will give
you some kind of pointers in the
direction it's a it's a constant process
it's never you have to jump out of of
your com comfort zone and get really
uncomfortable because all the growth all
the progress comes from that and I think
everybody has a tremendous amount of
potential but most of us uh you know we
we want comforter don't we we want nice
routine nice Comfort everything the way
it is status quo why change things I'm
comfortable enough so that is the enemy
of changing of of of raising your
standards so you have to do these things
to raise your standards maybe I I not
maybe I definitely will make a video
about this how to raise your standards
but yeah great
question Alan J Victor says we all know
that Hitler committed suicide but why
did he not escape to South America like
some other notorious
Nazi generals and scientists well is
it's good
question why did he commit
suicide so the question we have to ask
all our elv is what evidence do we have
that he committed
suicide do we have evidence of him
having committed suicide I mean you go
to Wikipedia they'll say or wherever
it'll say he committed suicide what
evidence do we have do we have his body
do we have pictures of him I mean there
are some very low resolution black and
white pictures of what what is alleged
to be his dead body and stuff but there
is no actual hard evidence
of Hitler having committed
suicide so there are theories okay I'm
not exposing this Theory or that but
there are
theories that claim that he indeed did
escape to South America and lived out
his life wherever in whatever Nation
just like Mel and Adolf akman and
whoever else akman was obviously
captured by the Israelis brought to
Israel and he was put to trial and
eventually hanged Adolf Aikman Clouts
Barbie was caught eventually when I was
a kid in France and Rudolf hes was in
jail in in the UK I think until he
committed suicide so so and so forth but
there is no evidence hard evidence in
controvert evidence that Hitler
committed
suicide it is said that the Soviets
found his body and they burned it or it
was half burned or whatever and they
took it away or whatever that's what is
claimed where's the hard evidence it
doesn't exist
I mean a piece of bone a piece of tissue
whatever that that can be you know
verified that it belong to him through
DNA evidence or whatever so it's not
there so there are theories that he
actually may have uh escaped are they
true are they untrue I don't know but
what I can tell you is that I have not
seen incontrovertible evidence of Hitler
having committed suicide but maybe he
did maybe he did who knows so this is
the thing about history there are lots
of gray areas that we don't quite know
about okay abishek Sam says can you
explain PX Romana and PX Americana the
word PX means peace p e a CE e peace in
Latin Latin was the language of Imperial
Rome the modern day Italian language is
a descendant language daughter language
of
Latin so PX Romana means Roman peace it
means
peace on the terms of the Roman Empire
and I don't remember who it was who said
that the Romans create a wasteland and
then they call it peace which means
they'll come into your country they will
devastate the country destroy everything
create a wasteland and then they will
say see we have imposed peace on the
nation we have pacified the nation this
is Roman peace backx Romana so that's
what it meant it meant that the Romans
ruled over a certain period of certain
area of the world and there was peace in
that area of the world but peace on
Roman
terms so when they conquer
Greece they pacify the nation kill off
the Kings and everything and then they
impos peace on the nation peace through
the Roman swords the Gladius so that was
Pax Romana peace imposed forcibly on a
nation by by defeating the nation and
militarily occupying the nation that was
PX rumana okay so it is it is not
something that was good for the for the
subjugated peoples for the subjugated
Nations but yes today people yearn for
that sort of thing the greatness and
Glory of Rome uh every day people think
about the Roman Empire apparently in the
west yeah and they think of it as a time
of great progress and whatnot okay yeah
sure there was progress but a lot was
destroyed in the process a lot was
destroyed in the process if you look at
Europe today there's only one script in
Western Europe which is the Latin
script well before the Romans stamped
their Authority everywhere there were
many more scripts the runic
scripts uh ogam was there various kinds
of runic scripts existed and much more
all those scripts were wiped out and the
Latin script was imposed everywhere and
the Latin script is not native to
Germanic languages like the like the
English language
the English language uses a non-native
script by the way and so on so that that
is Pax Romana it was it was
colonization it was imperialism and the
same thing applies to Pax Americana the
Americans have they essentially rulle
the world today whether you real realize
it or not they're the most influential
nation in the world today they are the
genuine visha Guru today the Americans
are the visha guru today and not just
the Vish Guru but the visha soldier the
V Vish ruler the visha superpower that's
what they are and the so-called
rules-based International order that
exists today is tax
Americana
um okay harit agrawal says what was the
reason behind the demise of chingis Khan
and who was his son so chingis Khan died
around 1227
ad um he died in China in present day
China he was in the process of uh of
subjugating the Western Shia Empire the
shisha
Empire and the process was not yet
completed and he died in the year
1227 and why did he die what was the
cause of his death is not known because
the only text the only text that we know
of that is the authoritative text for
The Life and Times of Shri chungus Khan
the secret history of the Mongols this
text does not speak about why why he
died or how he died so that is a matter
of mystery it is unknown what he died
off and then there are various
speculations but none has been proven
one speculation is that he got injured
in a battle with the shisha and he may
have died of his injuries another piece
of
speculation is that he had married a
princess
uh of the shisha and because he was once
again invading the shisha Empire and he
would have destroyed her people maybe
she stabbed him to death or or did you
know caused his death in some way or
poisoned him or something so there are
all these
speculations no proof of any of these
all we know is that he died in the year
1227 and apparently his last uh before
dying his last order apparently as it is
claimed was that shisha is to be
destroyed
annihilated and that was done after his
death so we don't know the reason for
for his demise but he died in the year
1227 or 1228 something like that check
it out I don't have all the memories
stored away in my brain small brain you
see okay now who was his son well he did
not have a single son he had multiple
Sons the first was Joi whose paternity
is kind of in doubt but he always
regarded Joi and always recognized him
as his son long story read it up if you
want Joi was the first son the second
son
was who was the second son was it
chagatai the third son was ogai and I
can think of at least three sons he
would have had daughters as
well uh but I can remember Three Sons
Joi chagatai OED and long before he died
significant amount of time before he
died he had decreed he had made the
statement he had proclaimed claimed that
it was ogai his third son who would
succeed him as the great Khan of the
Mongols and that was his word and his
word was carried out his wish was
carried out ogai became his successor
the second uh emperor of the Mongol
Empire so he had at least three sons
that that I can think of so ogeda was
the second Khan of the gurhan of pagan
of the Mongol Empire and uh I think it
was one of his one of chingis Khan's
grandsons kubl Khan went on to become
the Emperor of China and the first
emperor of the Yuan Dynasty and then
retrospectively chingis Khan was
proclaimed as the first emperor of the
Yuan Dynasty and so on so multiple sons
and we don't quite know how he
died okay parag Chan says can you throw
some light on King
vaham the the King of The perss Who
requested okay yeah King vaham which the
Persians requested to come and save them
from the Arabs okay yes the ballad of
King vaham is an ancient
sassanian
poem uh let me find that there is a guy
called Faria
faraji faraji on
YouTube so let me go to his YouTube
channel now I will not play the music
because I would get a copyright strike
here it is his music but I can show you
the channel and you could check it out
so uh this is the channel I think this
just gentleman is person if I'm not
mistaken now let's uh look for
vaham okay yeah The Ballad of King
vam and uh I will not play this for
obvious
reasons and what's the story behind this
the story is that
uh the Persians Persia has been invaded
by the Arabs okay so Persia has been
invaded by the Arabs and the Arabs have
killed the Persian kings and they are
destroying the the Persian temples Zan
temples and destroying the person
religion and so on and somebody writes
this poem saying that
uh saying that we need to send a
messenger to India so that we can inform
the Indians of what the Arabs have done
to us they've killed our Kings and
they're destroying our religion and we
hope that from India King vaham will
come with on elephants with very
powerful commanders and he
will uh evict the Arabs from Persia so
that's the kind of sad lament this poem
uh
represents um they wish that they could
send a messenger to India to inform the
Indians of what has happened so that
Indi so that the Indians can come and
save the Persians that's what the thing
is so what does that tell you about the
relations between India and Persia when
you are see the Arabic invasion of
Persia was the worst moment in the
history of Persia it was a time of
extreme
desperation the Kings the royalty
everything was destroyed their culture
civilization religion was on the verge
of being wiped out when you are at the
lowest point who will you remember you
will only remember those closest to you
right you won't remember your fair
weather friends you will only remember
those who are closest to you and the
ones who are the most closely related to
you so that kind of tells you that India
and Persia had this extremely closed
relation India and Persia never went to
war before the Arabic Invasion some
border skirmishes and and things they
happen even between Indian Kings so
that's no big deal even Brothers fight
right when you when it comes to Kings
and all that Brothers cousins they fight
what what is the Mahabharat it's cousins
fighting so that sort of small thing
would obviously have happened along the
border regions of India and Persia but
the Persians who were a tremendously mil
militaristically expansive people they
never ever tried to launch a fulls scale
or even a half-hearted military invasion
of India never happened until Persia
became
arabized so yeah it it kind of indicates
how close the kinship and cultural and
civilizational Bonds were between India
and Persia today you don't see that
today the Persians don't see India as as
kin because Persia no longer is kin you
know uh during the turkic occupation of
Persia last 3 400 years lots of
Outsiders were brought into Persia by
the by the turkic kings of the quasm
Empire and later
Empires uh if you look at Persia you
know the the uh Caucasus region lots of
people were were brought into pora from
the Caucasus region aarani people and
various people from the Caucasus and
that has significantly changed the
demographics of Iran if you go to Iran
today you will see a a certain
percentage of the people who look almost
European you know light eyes maybe blue
eyes or green eyes and light hair some
of them have blonde hair some have red
hair and light skin so lots of people in
Persia certain percentage look like that
if you look at Mr Ki Etc they kind of
look very uh almost European or turkic
at least but the but the true Persians
they have light brown skin dark eyes and
dark hair so that has kind of changed
the democra have changed and and the
thoughts thought process attitudes all
that has changed in Persia now so today
that closeness isn't there anymore
between India and Persia which
historically was a fact so this
poem The Ballad of King vaham is kind of
the last gasp of that when Persia was
being destroyed by the Arabs and their
One Last Wish was that maybe they were
hoping that India could be made aware of
what was happening and India will come
and save them didn't happened because at
that time India itself was not
politically unified under a single
Empire if India was UN unified under a
single Empire at the time who knows our
emperor who whoever it was may actually
have gone and rescued the Persians
but at the time it was not the case uh
the the Arabic invasion of Persia
happened at a time when there was no
single Empire in India it was multiple
there's this Cy cyclical process right
so that's where India was at the
time
okay um what else do we have lots of
questions Viv Kumar says any day the
Sentinel tribe of man and nicobar
collect to the real world is the Indian
government doing something in this area
okay let us talk about the Sentinel
Island so it's an island in the Andaman
and nicobar archipelago let's go in take
a look at it so I'll go to the satellite
imagery and we're going to go and find
the Sentinel Islands Sentinel Island so
I'm sure you all know where the Andaman
nicobar archipelago is
let's go let's dig in and do you see
this little island here the North
Sentinel Island that's the island we're
talking
about and you can see it's all Forest
it's not a very large island if you look
at the legend at the bottom of the map
you can see that the island is roughly
10 kilm or so okay 7.8 kilometers
wide and if you measure from here to
here it's about 9 kilm this way it's a
reasonably small island uh about 50
square kilometers or so roughly roughly
okay and you will see nothing here no
signs of human habitation or anything
you won't see any Huts any dwellings but
there are people who live here that is
known and I'm not going to try and dig
in and try and zoom in and find some
signs of habitation I think if you do
that you will find tracks you know
tracks left by people you can see
there's this what looks like a track
over here you know a walking trail or
something and you will see the these
things over here if you if you spend
some time looking at the island so you
have people living here but these people
have been living here in isolation for
about 30 or 40,000
years uh the British did kind of uh
occupy the island for a while and the
and the British left very bad memories
in the minds of these people which is
why they are extremely hostile today and
they don't want any kind of Outsiders
coming in and if if any Outsider comes
in and tries to approach the island then
they shoot arrows at them that is what
is known about their behavior so I think
a few decades ago the government of
India decided that this island will not
be uh nobody will be allowed to go to
the island we will respect the wishes of
the people of these this island we will
not allow anyone to go them go there let
them live their lives under our
protection but entirely autonomously so
you can say that North centran Island
the people of this island this island
itself is a self-governing island it is
kind of a protectorate of India it is
definitely part of the Indian Territory
but it has local governance I don't know
what form of governance it is but we
don't interfere with their life uh when
the earthquake and tsunami happened in
2004 we did send some helicopters to
take a look at what's happening and to
make sure that everybody is alive I
think uh they were all alive and they
were shooting arrows at the helicopter
which shows that they were okay uh so
that is the deal uh so they don't want
to connect with the rest of the world
they are living a life that can be
classified as a stone age kind of
existence that is their lifestyle they
are probably the last Stone Age tribe on
the surface of the planet there may be
some uncontacted tribes in the Amazon
rainforest but when it comes to the our
part of the world it's the only known
Stone Age
tribe so yeah that is the situation and
recently L some some
wonderfully intelligent American
missionary had tried to go there with a
Bible in his hand and um well didn't end
very well for him is all I'll
say
Okay
um okay let's see what other questions
do we have
J P says why in the world of intersexual
Dynamics men and women fight to destroy
the gender red pill men want to take
away women's human rights and feminism
wants to oppress men strange times look
this is a straight of the out of the
Marxist Playbook you create artificial
divisions of society you paint one
section of society as the oppressed you
paint another Society section of the
society is oppressors and then you make
them fight and you and then a small
group of people get the benefit of all
of this so right now what since the
1950s 60s feminism has been hijacked by
the by the left and they have created
this this artificial fight they paint
the men as the oppressors and the women
as the as the oppressed the evil toxic P
patriarchy right the
patriarchy so fight the patriarchy is
the is the slogan so now it's about
women fighting men and men are
oppressors so if a woman has a boy child
then she's going to regard that boy as
an oppressor I mean what kind of
incredible nonsense is that but that's
the level of of uh well the fight in
society that you have in the west today
and and that's now coming into India as
well feminism and gender studies
and what whatever right so this is being
taught to Indians as well these days in
university colleges and what
not and I don't know what this P ISS red
pill blue pill I think I think it comes
from the movie The Matrix right red pill
and blue pill Morpheus offers those two
pills to Neo I think red pill means you
wake up to the reality of the world and
blue pill means you'll stay asleep or
whatever oblivious to what's really
happening that sort of thing yeah it's
strange times strange times we're living
through and uh yeah it's not good it
never ends well when you're fighting
each other
okay geopolitical dubas says do you
believe in the stories of
Annabelle hav't seen the movie I think
it's a horror movie of some kind right
is it a doll a haunted doll is it a
haunted nun not sure
look it's all Supernatural stuff right I
am not a believer in the
Supernatural
um I'm more of a logical person no
rationalist as such when I hear the the
word rationalist it it sounds like
imbecile to
me yeah but anyway so I don't know about
the stories of Annabel
and all these gods and demons not gods
and demons it is what Satan right Satan
and his demons I don't believe in that I
don't believe in Satan I don't believe
in hell I don't believe in the Demons of
Satan and whatever else nah not for
me um
Weiss says your opinion on oen and is
obes obesity mostly
genetic I think this oen pic is some
kind of drug isn't it a weight loss drug
fat burning drug of some kind I've heard
of it vaguely I'm not sure how it works
what's the mechanism of action uh if it
is famous it it mean probably means that
it works to a certain
extent well good then if if it works but
I'm not sure how good it is how
efficacious it is and how safe it
is uh so I I don't really know about
that about the mechanism of the drug how
it works and all that is obesity mostly
genetic I think some people have a
predisposition for various kinds of
addictions some people uh find it easy
to get addicted to alcohol or or tobacco
or gambling or
carbohydrates uh so carbohydrates is is
what causes obesity when you uh ingest
excessive amounts of
carbohydrates of course if you eat a lot
of you know protein and fat also it
it'll make you fat but when it comes to
the very harmful kind of obesity it is
generally carbohydrates that do that
because it doesn't just make you fat it
messes up your entire system through
within it it uh causes damage in your
liver in your pancreas in your kidneys
it elevates your insulin thing it it
creates insulin resistance which has
extremely bad harmful effects on the
cardiovascular system itself as well it
can cause Strokes it can cause uh
hypertension it can cause heart attacks
that's all
carbohydrates so it is possible that
some people may have this genetic
predisposition to becoming addicted to
carb heavy
Foods you know sugary stuff and and
refined flowers and refined material ref
hyper Ultra refined Ultra processed
foods and all that and these days you
have all these cheap seed oils and all
which which add fuel to the fire on top
of what you already have and so on so um
at the end of the day obesity is all
about calories in calories out obviously
not each not every calorie is the same
if you eat 100 calories of just from
sugar if you eat 100 calories from
vegetables and fruits and if you eat 100
calories from meat these are all
different the calories you will get from
sugar 100 calories are going to be just
pure 100 calories if you eat 100
calories worth of vegetables and fruits
your body will have to work to process
the fiber and all that so it's going to
end up burning some of the calories it
it gets from the food and the same goes
for for protein and fat but sugar and
carbs which is in the form of sugar
that's almost pure calories it will just
spike your insulin so so even the
calories are in the same even though
they're technically the same calories so
100 gram of sugar is not the same as 100
gram of vegetables which is not the same
as 100 gram of let's say milk or meat
it's all different so overall I think
there
is some genetic component to obesity
it's it's quite
possible Yash Singh says your thoughts
on Kumari kandam and old geographical
map of India look there's no evidence of
Kumari kandam anywhere and I can show
you that let's go back to the map here's
the map on on the screen let's put the
satellite image on now we can see the
satellite image in the satellite image
you can see the bottom of the oceans as
well and you can almost see the tracks
that the Indian subcontinent Left Behind
when it moved away from
Africa and made its way across the
Indian Ocean and eventually slammed into
the Eurasian continent you can see the
tracks left behind by the movement of
the Indian subcon over the past 120
million years so you can see what's at
the bottom of the ocean and please show
me where is the L where is the Lost
Continent if there was a continent that
went under the ocean you would see some
trace of it
undeniably it simply cannot hide where
is this lost continent there is no such
thing and therefore I can tell you for
sure that you know in the past some land
may have been lost for sure under the
ocean you can see over there's a
continental shelf yes you can see the
continental shelf and when the uh when
the world was much colder then a lot
more land would have been above the
ocean and as the ocean started Rising
many cities would have been lost to the
Sea we know multiple such cases we know
of dwara in Western India we know of the
entire Gulf of kbat archaeological
complex which is a whole network a whole
complex of underwater cities that are at
least 10,000 years old we have cities
like cavari pum PanAm Etc in in you know
uh of the eastern Southeastern coast of
India sunken submerged cities exist here
as well so we know that cities have
disappeared under the ocean but no such
case of a entire continent disappearing
under the ocean that there is zero
evidence of so that is what I can tell
you from the evidence that we have if
you have other evidence please show me
I'll be willing to consider that
objectively
okay poomi says if the Elder son of a
king inherits the kingdom then what
happened to the other Sons well it
depends on the context it depends on on
which culture which civilization which
nation you're talking about if you're
talking about the Turks the otoman
Empire do you know what happened when
the Ottoman Empire had a transfer of
power let's go to the let's go to our
dear friend Wikipedia yeah uh one second
one second let's go to otoman
Empire um let me put that on the screen
we we'll do Google search for Ottoman
Empire we're going to trace some things
back okay let's get into the Ottoman
Empire and who is there one of the
greatest Kings it's Saleem right uh not
Saleem saleim was the son uh we're going
to talk about um suan The Magnificent
obviously uh where is
that okay suan the Magnificent so this
guy comes to power and he has all these
children
um
Sons so see suan the first had at least
eight Sons shahade Mahmud he dies on
29th October 1520 shahade Murad 19th
October 20
1520 Shazad Mustafa executed by the
order of his father 6th October 1553 6
November and so on so there are
different dates over here but who was
the jangar
jangar who was the guy who succeeded
Sultan Saleem II right s the S sale the
drunkard how many sons did he
have um aha so this guy his his son was
Murad the eldest son and all the other
sons died on the 22nd of December
1574 22nd December 1574 22nd December
1574 all executed by Murad the Third
but the son who succeeded so in the case
of this guy Murad theii when he became
the king he executed all of his siblings
I mean male siblings what about this
guy's Sons I suspect that all of his
sons would also have died in the year
1595 okay so that was the tradition in
the Ottoman Empire and it is something
that somebody like orze also kind of
continued in India he was also a Turk
wasn't he orze so in the turkic
tradition when when the eldest son
becomes the king or becomes the takes
over the crown from the father then the
moment he takes the crown he's going to
execute all of his blood all of his male
siblings all of his brothers and
possibly even some cousins to ensure
that nobody else can clean the throne
that was the kind of extraordinary
system they had the
Turks so in the turky tradition the
eldest son of the king would immediately
upon taking the crown execute all of his
male siblings all of his brothers in
India in other countries it was not
quite the case I mean if in the in the
UK you have William and whoever else
right uh who's the current King it's
Charles right Charles Charles with the
fingers uh he has male siblings he has
Brothers wonderful brothers so he didn't
execute with those upon becoming the
king so that's not the case over there
um in the Christian tradition it wasn't
always the case that they would kill
their male siblings in India not the
case we've had I mean in the in the
Indian indigenous Traditions it was not
the case for example we know of Lord Ram
he had how many
brothers lakman bat shatu shatrugna did
he do anything to them no upon upon
getting the crown even when his his
kingdom was taken away from him he
volunt really just went with it right so
it depends on the cultural
civilizational context in which this
transition happens in the case of
chingis Khan he ensured that his third
son becomes the next Emperor and his
first and second son agreed to that they
had no choice and so on okay so it
depends
um uh cute animal says can you say that
democracy is perfect or the best so is
democracy the best system the perfect
system no no I don't agree that it's the
best there is no perfect system there is
no best system look at Singapore how it
was completely transformed in a matter
of 20 years by a dictator you had a
benevolent dictator Lee Kuan Yu who
completely transformed Singapore and
that is a dictatorship so you can have
dictators who work who who genuinely
work for the people and for the nation
who spend their whole life working for
the people in the nation you can have
dictators doing that and in democracy
you can have quite the opposite in many
cases so there is no perfect system
there is no best system what matters is
the quality of the leadership in any
system whichever system you you have as
long as the leadership is
great you're going to be very well off
and no matter what system you're in if
the leadership is bad
well and the gods save you may the God
Save
You clous hellstar QT says will Pluto
and Neptune collide one day not that I
know of
no actually it's an interesting question
that you ask because the orbit of Pluto
kind of comes within the orbit of
Neptune for a certain amount of for a
certain amount of its path but um as far
as I know there is no danger of the two
uh objects colliding any time in the
foreseeable
future um not that I know of but
interesting question that you ask and I
I I get where you where where you coming
from the orbits kind of are weird um the
orbit of Pluto comes inside the orbit of
Neptune for a certain amount of it its
path so that's
interesting
okay uh Malik said says watching you
since the Ukraine Invasion thoughts on
the current situation there nothing much
much has changed over the past few
months um there's something or other
going on it's it's a very slow War
grinding out kind of situation right now
various battles have been called meat
grinders that's how horrible it is and
the reason why the progress is so slow
kind of a stalemate
thing on a good day there is an advance
of two of two or3 kilometers here or
there that sort of thing why is it like
that it's
because because of the technological
advancements that have been brought into
play in this war the battlefield
environment is extremely
lethal tanks have become extremely
vulnerable today to various kinds of
drones loitering Munitions suicide
drones um where if it come when it comes
to individual soldiers infantry there
are small drones that are designed to
take out individual soldiers and you see
those horrible
scenes uh on social media horrible
horrible absolutely horrible and
that these drones don't kill the guy
immediately but they ensure that he is
out of action and then it's not a good
death so the battlefield environment has
become extremely lethal there are mines
everywhere anti-tank mines antipersonnel
mines so it's very difficult to advance
right now and also the the fact is that
Mr Putin as he seems to be uh willing to
wait as as long as
necessary for the West to give up on
Ukraine because it's clear that the
Russians are winning no matter what you
say I lots of people will be watching
Indian news and foreign news and all the
Indian news channels are just puppets
they just parrot what the Western media
is saying because they because you don't
have any Indian reporters on the ground
on both sides initially you had some
news leaders who had gone to Ukraine and
they were they were reporting about the
the war from the Ukrainian side if you
are a genuinely unbiased and balanced
News Channel you would send two news
readers to one side to new to the other
side so that you can have reporting from
both sides so that you know what's
really happening from both perspectives
but no they will only send reporters and
news readers to the Ukrainian side
that's the kind of media coverage you
have in India so the Indian media
coverage is not going to give you the
right information it's going to give you
skewed information and when it comes to
the Western media whether it's a French
media or the German media the Ukrainian
Media or the British Media or the
American Media obviously it's propaganda
and narratives they have been saying for
the past three I don't know what years
two years at least that Putin is dying
of something or the other he had what
some form of cancer he has something
else he's been dying he's on the verge
of death well he's still around he's
just fine they have been saying that
Russia has lost hundreds of thousands of
soldiers they're on the verge of running
out of ammunition well they've been
saying that for the past 2 and a half
years what happened
they were saying that bahmut was
completely completely useless I don't
know why the Russians are fighting well
the Russians won so the point is what
you are consuming from the news media if
it is the mainstream media is mostly
propaganda and agenda driven narratives
you have to look at a 360 degree picture
everybody's trying to spew
propaganda uh that's the thing but the
way I'm seeing it Ukraine
um the war when whenever it ends will
end on Russia's terms not on NATO's
terms and it may last a long time it
could be a frozen conflict a slow War
scenario or it could end in the next two
weeks who knows who knows depending on a
variety of
factors uh so yeah that's what I think
of what's going on there right now
oh no this is a very dangerous question
swapnil says what such in tendar selfish
sir I am a very small person I cannot
speak about great people I I I will very
wisely not answer not not feeld such
questions I will just leave the ball
alone
uh endan says I wonder why most of the
lgbtq people in India are extremely
Hindu phobic extremely anti-hindu anti
Modi Pro Western ideologist extremely
pro pro Congress Pro Congress allies why
so look I don't know too many uh lgbtq
people uh I know abijit arra who who is
who has well said it himself that he is
he's gay and he is not hinduphobic he's
not anti anti-india and all that so
that's one
example good he's a great guy uh I don't
know any other lgbtq people that I can
think of uh
personally I'm sure I may know people
but we don't know if they are that or
not right it's entirely A Private Matter
I don't care about that right so um I
don't know but there there does there
does seem to be some kind of uh such
tendency of
uh of LGBT lgbtq people who seem to be
some of them at least seem to be kind of
Hindu phobic which is strange because I
think Hinduism is the only religion that
has never oppressed or oppressed them or
done anything that is
anti-lgbtq I mean in in the UK I I I
keep seeing these these news reports of
people who are lgbtq people who have
same seex marriages and they have Hindu
weddings because no other religion is
willing to give them religious wedding
so they have Hindu weddings I recently
saw some two two ladies who got married
in the UK in a Hindu ritual Vic ritual
so I think when comes to all the
religions in the world it is the dharmic
religions and especially Hinduism who
are the
most
benign towards the lgbtq people there is
absolutely nothing in the past 10,000
10,000 years of Indian history not a
single instance will you find of any
anti lgbtq plus 23 whatever any such
activity nothing nothing nothing
whatsoever and yet they are anti-india
anti- Hinduism and all that I I don't
get it so clearly they are being
brainwashed in some way those who have
these Tendencies for some reason in some
manner I think they all go through the
Indian education system don't they I
think the education system is where all
the rot uh the root the source of all
the rot is there that's what I can
say
Okay McLovin says why is the tax so high
in India the taxpayers here don't get
any benefits it actually attracts more
problems I don't know why tax is so high
in India it's not as high as the US for
example the US has ridiculous amounts of
tax 40 plus perc I think but yes India
also has a tremendous amount of tax and
you know what some people will say it's
only 1.2% of Indians who pay income tax
so India actually has the lowest amount
of tax paying in the in the world that's
the kind of thing many people will say
less than 2% of Indians pay income tax
do you know something you buy a bottle
of
Kola you buy a pencil you buy an
eraser you buy a textbook a notebook you
buy a
car you buy groceries you buy whatever
you paying taxes on everything you buy a
bottle of aspirin you buy a b bottle of
of parasitol anything that you buy any
service any good that you pay for you're
paying tax on that
you every single Indian is a taxpayer
you're already paying taxes but those
unfortunates who pay income tax will
first get a salary pay 20 30 whatever
percent of that they will get some money
whatever is left they have to pay more
tax on that every time they purchase
something so they're being taxed
multiple
times they're being taxed over and over
again it's a tremendous burden why not
simplify the tax everybody sure but tax
only on what you buy that's it why do
you need income tax and this tax and
that tax and what not keep the system
simple everybody should contribute to
the nation everybody should pay tax to
the government that the government can
use that to BU to for nation building I
agree no question about
it but don't make it an honorous burden
on the people of India that half their
time is spent you know chasing tax tax
and whatnot tax filing and GST filing
and blah blah blah so much of energy is
wasted in this when you can just have a
simple
system so I agree this the tax regime
needs to be greatly simplified we don't
have to follow the example of the West
in everything we don't have to blindly
ape the West why don't we set an example
for the rest of the world as to how a
taxation system should be vishnugupta
chanaka said you should tax lightly not
too lightly but not too heavily either
maybe 20 25%
maximum and make it a single
straightforward thing so don't tax
people for the on the income they they
are earning just tax people on whatever
they're
spending just one tax so I think it can
be simplified greatly but I don't know
why our bureaucrats love complexity and
love making Indians run in circles and
jump through hoops because that's where
their that's the source of their power
right but it's up to the leaders to
change things and the bureaucrats are
supposed to just carry out the policies
right
so I I wish something some improvements
are
made
uh cracker says please make a video on
Islam's golden age
uh Islam's Golden
Age yeah that I can think about that
that's an interesting period of History
it will obviously attract controversy
because we know what was the source of
the golden age of Islam okay anyway I
I'll consider this thank
you shiram SEL says is an asteroid going
to hit the earth in the year 2038 um
I've heard of some news like that that
there's an asteroid that has a a nonzero
probability of its path intersecting
with that of the Earth in the year 2038
now how close is going to be the
approach we don't know but there seems
to be a nonzero
non-trivial probability that the paths
May intersect so we still don't know for
sure it could happen and there are
multiple such asteroids which are called
near Earth asteroids whose orbits around
the sun do intersect with the orbit of
the Earth but some but they're not
always in the same place at the same
time but these are near Earth asteroids
and they have to be tracked very
rigorously and the problematic asteroids
are not the ones that are known it is
the ones that we don't know about
because this the Soro system is enormous
it's all dark asteroids are tiny many
asteroids are really dark Carboniferous
asteroids and all that dark like suot
it's very hard to discover them and you
never know you know one of of those days
they may discover an asteroid and call
that asteroid
Kali I wish it never happens but one of
these days it will happen maybe while
humans are alive maybe way in the future
but it's going to happen
eventually Nishan
says did India ever have slave culture
had an argument with my American friend
of course we had slavery in India when
the Turks ruled India we had
slavery you know you've heard of the
mamluk dynasty the slave Dynasty balban
ilish razah Sultana Etc that was a
short-lived dynasty of mamluks slave
soldiers and they had slaves of their
own so as long as India was ruled by the
Turks you had widespread slavery in
India they would take millions of
Indians as slaves
men women children for different
purposes I'm sure you can imagine what
purposes this would be so you had
slavery in India then when you had the
Europeans in India they also kept
slaves for them it is natural it's part
of their
culture I mean think of Christopher
Columbus when he reached uh when he
reached the Americas he thought he had
reached India and when he saw those
people the natives who came to help him
and greet him the first thing he said
was that look at this fine people they
will make such great
slaves it's part of their
culture when it comes to Indian culture
slavery never
existed there was never ever any slavery
in India under Indian
Kings or EMP or
Emperors you had servants the term Das
in in Sanskrit means servant not
slave okay
okay but some historians will try to
misconstrue that to mean slave that's
not the case that's a lie Dasa means
servant right so India never head
slavery I mean what was that guy's name
mastan the the the Greek ambassador to
India he wrote Indians don't have slaves
Indians don't there's no single slave in
India seven classes or occupations in
India and Society s seven social
societal divisions but no slavery
and lots of other people have spoken
about this there was no slavery in India
ever okay never under Indian Kings or
Queens but certainly for a thousand
years or so roughly under foreign
occupiers of
India so yep that is the answer but
listen don't what's the point of arguing
with people no
one it's it's very rare to find people
who will actually look at things
objective L and actually change their
mind change their opinion based on
information most
people they don't want to change their
mind so there's no point arguing with
people you
know so I generally don't get into
arguments unless U usually I don't I try
my best not
to
um
okay some other question
questions Master hites says light cannot
Escape black holes it means that the
escape velocity for black holes would be
more than the speed of light is it
possible find displacement for velocity
D in black hole will be zero okay I'm
not sure what the last part is but okay
um light cannot Escape black holes does
it mean that the escape velocity for a
black hole exceeds the speed of light
yes yes Escape is velocity is a very
straightforward uh formula let me uh
Google that I'll not derive it over here
but let me Google that uh escape
velocity let us put that on the screen
we're going to Google
that escape ve
velocity escape velocity Celestial
mechanics
so so this is what it is in es escape
velocity the escape velocity speed at
the distance D from the center of a
spherically symmetric primary body such
as a star or planet with mass m is given
by the formula ve is the square root of
2 mg by D where G is the Newton's
gravitational constant m is the mass of
the thing and so on so forth so for a
black hole do they have it for a black
hole let me try and search for
that okay so at the Event Horizon of any
black Hool the escape Velocity is equal
to the speed of light and if you go
beyond the Event Horizon the escape
Velocity exceeds the speed of light
which tells you that photons simply
cannot escape from the black hole if
they are closer to the black hole center
than the Event Horizon the radius of the
Event Horizon so yes that's what it
means that's why light cannot Escape
black holes but of course you have
Quantum effects which cause the black
holes to radiate it's called Hawking
radiation that's a whole different
phenomenon s bador says some leftists
are spreading the propaganda that
brahans destroyed nalanda what's your
take my take is that it is a it is
reible it is asinine it is laughable
that brahmins destroyed Nanda brahmins
were not Warriors brahans weren't these
yolked jacked people they were Scholars
brahmins tried to continue the tradition
of nalanda after the destruction of
nalanda by
bakari uh I don't know who it was I
think it was a Tibetan monk who had come
to India to investigate nalanda he found
that it's in Ruins but there is one
teacher one Brahman who was still
conducting classes that that Brahman
gentleman his name was Rahul Shri bhadra
he was in his 90s and he was still
trying to conduct classes for a handful
of students in the ruins of Nanda
the brahmins were trying to preserve
nalanda they tried to continue the
tradition as as as long as possible it
was the Ki what bakar Ki who destroyed
nalanda that tur Barbarian and you know
what eventually happened to him right he
met his end in Turkey uh in
Tibet and um his
uh would you like to know what happened
to bakar kji he was skinned his body was
skinned let let's let's try and uh see
if we can find
that
um let's Google
that um not
now so that
guy I believe his body was skinned and
the skin was preserved in T in in
Tibet
um okay not sure whether I can find that
because there is kind of sto an episode
of History that's not very well known
but the the Crux of the matter is that
it was not brahmins who destroyed
nalanda it was bakar kji the Turk who
destroyed
nalanda and leftists or whoever it is
will will do their job it's our job not
to believe this nonsense
right
okay Luffy 07 says who has more right to
claim Tibet India or China based on
history India has never administered or
ruled Tibet Indians have lived in Tibet
India has influenced Tibet deeply
tremendously Tibetan culture
is a local form of Indian culture
synchronized synchronized with the local
in ancient culture uh so India has never
ever ruled Tibet never administered
Tibet never invaded or occupied Tibet
India has never done that but and Tibet
had the best of relations essentially we
are the same culture ethnically we are
different peoples but culturally we are
same we understand completely the
Tibetan script is a descend of the B
script it is you could consider it to be
a variant of
the similar to the similar to the
Mongolian swo
script Google
that uh so that's the deal with between
India and Tibet what about China the
Chinese have no claim on Tibet they have
never ruled Tibet their flimsy claim
claim on Tibet is is based on the claim
that the Yuan Dynasty once ruled Tibet
and the according to the Chinese the
Yuan dynasty was a Chinese dynasty it
was not a Chinese D Dynasty it was a
conquest Dynasty and the conquest was
done by the great Shri chingis Khan and
the Emperors of the Yuan Dynasty were
Mongols they were not
Chinese and they did not invade conquer
or occupy Tibet Tibet was their
protectorate Tibet was the guru of the
Yuan Empire there was a guru shisha
relationship Master student relationship
Tibet was the master
in what in
Buddhism okay Tibet the Tibetans were
the gurus of the Mongols and they
brought they taught Buddhism to to
Mongolia so Tibet was the intermediary
that brought Indian culture into
Mongolia where it still exists it's
deeply
ingrained so the Chinese claim to Tibet
is is an entirely fictitious made up
flimsy grounds but they own they they
occupy Tibet and possession is 9/10 of
the law so to say so to
speak so that is the ca that is the deal
that's the case nobody has a right to
Tibet Tibet should be entirely
independent that's my opinion and when
in the future Tibet will eventually be
independent I think India and Tibet will
have an open border the kind of
relationship we have with Nepal right
now so yeah that is how I see it
okay rajat hatwar says will India have
compulsory military service if World War
I happens for age 18 to 30 or more than
that if World War I happens I think
there could be recruitment there could
be
conscription and in such a case I think
everybody every able-bodied man should
go and uh enlist in the armed forces we
do not ever want World War II to happen
of course okay but if there is an
emergency like that then yeah I suppose
there could be that sort of thing and I
don't think anybody would run from that
I mean it's it's a it's a privilege to
have the opportunity to serve your
nation and your people so I think
everybody would be happy to do that so
if there is World War I which which I
hope never happens then there in that
hypothetical situation there could be
possibly compulsory conscription
H good question sidar Kumar says uh
what's the story behind the Mongol
invasion of at the Assassins Brotherhood
in the 13
Century okay good good question
interesting question
uh the
hashishin the hashishin were
uh they were the Assassins the the
legendary but very real assassins of
History they were called the hashishin
because their assassins
the trained assassins would would ingest
opium hashish and go get high on that
and they would go and carry out their
mission high on
hashish and the mission would be a
suicide mission
always even if they succeeded in
assassinating the target they would get
killed and they would ensure that
whether they successful or than not they
will not be C caught alive they would
ensure that so the were called hashishin
assassins they were
Shi uh 12 ismile Shia if I'm not
mistaken and they had this Fortress
called
alamut which is in Ruins today and the
reason it is in ruined it was an
inaccessible Fortress let's Google that
shall we let us Google The Fortress of
Al
Amud
um oh not this let us go to the
uh Google yeah
Google alamut
foress okay Castle it's in Iran today
it's on this on top of this uh Hill it's
almost impossible to reach there okay uh
and uh it so it was essentially an
impregnable Fortress and it's in this
region where which is quite cold where
there you have a lot of snow for a
significant part of the year and so on
maybe it looked something like this in
the past I mean that's an that's a
historical depiction of some kind and
this Fortress even though it's almost
inaccessible it was taken by chingis
Khan and the Grand Old Man of the
Mountain the the head of the order was
was uh eliminated by chingis Khan and
his armed forces and why did the Mongols
go after the the Assassins is the
question it's because apparently they
made an attempt on the life of jingus
Khan so they had to be taken out okay
all
right um we getting we're coming to the
end of today's
session
um adir chavda says why did countries
agree uh
to to use the US dollar as the world's
Reserve currency didn't they know that
the US could print their money and raise
their economy without causing inflation
look when the Roman
Empire imposes a
new rule on the
world what do you do you're going to
stand up to them you won't so in 1944
when the World War II was well it the
writing was on the wall it would end
sooner or later and the Allies would win
then it was clear that the US was the
dominant Force by the time the US had
this
inexhaustible amount of resources from
its entire continent sized land mass it
had the world's most powerful military
at the time it it had already got this
tremendous power projection ability so
it made sense for all the nations to
quietly acqu to what the US said
the US had a lot of Leverage okay and
all the other nations were way too weak
compared to the US uh so uh these
countries agreed to the US dollar and at
that time the US dollar was pegged to
the price of
gold so the US dollar was pegged to the
gold
standard which meant that the US dollar
the paper was a proxy for actual gold
you could if you had a US dollar you
could go to the Americans to the to
their bank and demand the say that
quantity of gold and they would have to
honor that that was the deal and that
went on until what 1970 or something the
Nixon Kissinger era and it was Nixon who
uh it was Nixon who ended that who
delink the US dollar from the gold
standard and he turned the US dollar
into a fiat
currency and that's where everything
changes and there's a website called WTF
happened in
1971 check it out it tells you it shows
you through
graphs everything that has gone wrong in
the US started in
1971 um yeah so that's the deal so when
the US dollar was agreed upon as the
world's Reserve currency it was it was
linked to the gold standard it was
linked to the price of gold it was a
genuine proxy for gold and then the
Americans went back on their word in
1970 or 71 or whenever when Nixon
decided to delink the US dollar from the
from the price price of
gold
okay mango says do you think that
marijuana should be legalized in India
what would be the outcome if it is
legalized
um I don't know look I don't think it
should be criminalized it's just a herb
obviously it's a psychotropic herb it
has all these hallucinatory or whatever
effects if you ingest that I don't think
most Indians have any interest in
marijana uh it is something it's it's
kind of a sacred ritual right on
shivaratri or whatever once or twice a
year that when people will will ingest
it ritualistically for religious
purposes and get a little high or
whatever uh that's the deal apart from
that it it just grows wild in various
parts of of India especially in the
hills and whatnot how do you criminalize
that I think it's already kind of semile
legal
right uh a small quantity of marijuana
that's found on somebody I don't think
it's a legal it's it's it's a criminal
offense it's only if someone's trying to
transport certain large quantities of
marij I don't know what the limit is
then it's a criminal offense so I don't
think it's something that's in high
demand it's anyway readily available I
suppose you could grow it in your
backhead if you wanted to I don't think
there's a high demand for this thing in
India I'm sure it has medicinal
properties the the CBD oil or whatever
seems to be good for certain
conditions um I've heard about
that so I think if it is fully legalized
I don't think there should be any big
change in
society there's no huge demand that we
people will start shipping tons of
marijuana somewhere or the other there's
no need for that I suppose so first of
all I don't think it is completely
illegal I think it's kind of semi-legal
or something in India and secondly that
I don't think there's a huge demand for
it I don't think most people even care
about it and whatever use it has has a
limited religious use that once or twice
a year on shivratri Etc people will do
that yeah so that's what I think
okay Rasika says Ashok killed all his
siblings good point so it's not always
that you get this I
mean that's that's a very good point you
make so it is said according to the
legend that ashoke had 99 brothers and
half brothers and he had them all killed
yeah so Ashok was kind of an exception
as we know he did he was called Chand
Ashok he was kind see he was definitely
one of our greatest Emperors okay as and
was great for the country as far as as
long as you were far away from him if
you were anywhere near him you you could
be in deep trouble he was a dangerous
guy but he was a great emperor and
during his time India prospered like
anything but he was a cruel guy and he
was kind of kind of perhaps kind of
crazy he had all those uh he he
persecuted the ajivikas didn't he and um
I don't know how many he had killed he
had this tor of chanber called ashoka's
narak or something in which he had his
all his political opponents tortured to
death and whatnot he was crazy kind of
guy so there are always exceptions
according to Indian culture you don't do
such things you simply don't do that but
there are exceptions right danand was an
exception he was a bad Emperor so
Chandra Gupta
Maia uh ended the nand Empire right
because they were corrupt and they were
not likeed by the people then you had uh
I can give you some more examples k k
Mama the the maternal Uncle of Krishna
Shri Krishna Kana was a very evil King
despite being dharmic supposedly so
there are always exceptions in every
culture but in the case of India it is
the exception not the rule that Kings
will when they come to power they will
kill their siblings okay it is it is a
rarity that such a thing will happen
obviously in any so Society no matter
how peaceful a certain percentage of the
population no matter how small the
percentage is a certain percentage will
have criminal Tendencies I think it's a
psychological thing not a cultural thing
so you can't say that because 0.1% of
your population has criminal Tendencies
it doesn't mean that your culture is a
criminal culture right that's not the
thing but yes you make a very good point
according to what we know Ashoka did
kill off all his siblings and a half
siblings very uh dangerous guy to be
around okay let's take a couple of more
questions oh we have already crossed two
hours wow didn't
realize
um okay let's take this one arush says
why did the US bomb Laos even though
Laos was not directly participating in
the Vietnam war is a good question let
us go to Google maps in case some of us
may not know where Laos
is so we know where India is we go
eastwards we see Myanmar then we see
Thailand and east of Thailand SW Nai we
have Laos this longish nation which is
west of Vietnam that's Laos and the US
so when the Vietnam War happened the US
did these tremendously heavy and
horrific bombing runs over Laos they
bombed Laos into Oblivion despite LA's
not being involved in the Vietnam War at
all why did the Americans do that
because what if some Vietnamese enemies
of the US were hiding in Laos let's
destroy Laos as well as simple as that
they are ruthless there's no human
rights there's no democracy when it
comes to the Americans fighting their
Wars they'll flatten everything the
American style of War fighting is
essentially the same as the old Roman
style you create a
Wilderness and you call it peace you
flatten entire nations and then say that
we have brought human rights and peace
and democracy because see there's no one
there now it's all peaceful that's what
the US does they
exfoliated Laos and Vietnam by using
this horrific carcinogen Called Agent or
orange they would spray that from their
aircraft in over forests so it would
over time defoliate all the all the
trees all the leaves would fall off but
that chemical would seep into the soil
and into the food chain it caused
horrific birth defects which still
persist in Vietnam and
Laos cancers birth defects malformed
children all that sort of thing which
goes on for Generations it's kind of
what they did in Hiroshima and Nagasaki
that sort of thing but maybe even
worse uh and there are still millions of
unexploded bombs all over the place
Vietnam and Laos and Laos was in no way
involved in this but just in case some
some Viet Kong were fight were hiding in
Laos let's destroy Laos as well that's
what they did so there you have
it all right so many more
questions um
Dr J shanka says uh if our politicians
keep uh playing cast politics Will
Hindus ever be able to unite will
Indians will ever be able to unite if
never then what's the most practical way
to eradicate this system it's very
simple how to eradicate this so-called
cast thing you know remove all
references to cast from your birth
certificate from your school certificate
from your educational certificates from
a government certificates remove cast
from there it becomes irrelevant
overnight your birth certificate has
cast on it your school certificates and
educational certificates Etc have cast
your government certificates and
whatever not everything is cast you the
government is perpetuating this weird
artificial unnecessary system remove all
references to cast from everywhere from
all the official documents that's it end
of story and then end all the
reservations and give reservations give
give reservations based on financial
status only you should give reservations
to those who are financially backward
for a generation or two maximum that's
it until they can come back come back to
the you know where they should be that's
it that's how you eradicate the system
practically uh Muhammad is says can you
shed some light on Mansa musa's trip to
mkah and how he devalued the value of
gold in Egypt so Mali let's go to
Mali so we will go to Africa now and in
Western
Africa in the Sahel region there is this
nation called Mali and there used to be
kingdom of Mali here a few centuries ago
much larger than the current Nation
present the nation of Mali and Mali is
rich in Gold it has tremendous gold
reserves and Mana Musa was this King Who
had who was reputedly the richest person
of all time so his net worth in today's
US dollar amounts would have been about
400 or so trillion dollars that's how
rich he was that's how much gold he had
I forget which century he lived in but
you can Google it and then obviously he
was a Muslim so he decided that he would
go to Mecca on a pilgrimage and uh as
you can see if you want to go to Mecca
to the uh Arabian Peninsula then from
Mali you have to go eastwards you have
to cross Egypt and go into Arabia so
Egypt obviously was a major economy at
the time reasonably prosperous nation
and I'm sure there was lot to buy over
there so Mana Musa I think was
he went on a shopping spree or something
and spent a lot of
gold in Egypt and he he flooded Egypt
with so much gold that it actually
devalued the value of gold in the
country so that's the long and the short
of it uh he had that much gold and when
you makes so much of that available its
value goes down so that's why the value
of gold temporarily plummeted in
Egypt uh that's the deal with manam Musa
[Music]
um
uhar sha says was bodybuilding popular
in Ancient India like we have samudra
gupta's muscular depiction in coins of
Gupta period uh we don't know we have
kind of lost
uh lost the information about the
practices of those days uh we know we
had martial arts various kinds of
martial arts in India
uh uh what's his name
uh Buddha Dharma the monk who went to
China he took the knowledge of India's
martial arts and transfer it to China
didn't he so there was that we had
martial arts in India and possibly
bodybuilding may also have been popular
I mean who doesn't like aesthetic
physics and all that and we know the
Gupta coins
right the coins let me try and Google
quickly uh
some Samra Gupta coin
so yeah you have these golden coins with
extremely powerful physical
depictions was this kta was it Kumar
Gupta one
second let's try Kumar
Gupta yeah you can see these Marshall
poses know bodybuilder kind of body
extremely fit bodies and all that see
here a heroic pose look at the bulging
muscles so yeah it may have been there I
mean you know the practice of
bodybuilding may have existed so we see
this indirect evidence over here on
these coins you can see the bulging
muscles and the aesthetic
physique good to see so it's look it
looks like bodybuilding may have been
popular in Ancient India all right we
have gone way past two hours 11 minutes
so I'm going to end this session over
here thank you so much for to everybody
who has participated apologies to those
of you whose questions I could not take
I know there are so many more questions
but I'm going to have to end it over
here we're going to have a live stream
again tomorrow tomorrow's live stream is
about science astrophysics all that and
then we will have live stream number 200
on Friday so hopefully I will see you in
these in these live streams coming up
until then take care and as
always keep raising your standards see
you see you soon bye